A Guide to the Danville (Va.) Civil Rights Case Files, 1963-1973
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Danville (Va.) Civil Rights Case Files, 1963-1973
Library of Virginia
38099
5 microfilm reels and 39 compact discs
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for microfilming and digital duplication by Danville, Virginia Circuit Court, 17 August 1999.
Historical Information
The summer of 1963 witnessed a wave of civil rights demonstrations throughout the nation. In Danville, Virginia, the leaders of the Danville Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC), inspired by events in Birmingham, Alabama, organized a series of protests of their own. Rev. Lawrence G. Campbell, Rev. Alexander I. Dunlap, Julius E. Adams, and Arthur Pinchback, believing that the Danville NAACP under the leadership of Doyle Thomas was too conservative, had founded the Danville SCLC in 1960. These men, along with Rev. Lendall W. Chase, president of the Danville SCLC, took the lead in promoting civil rights in Danville, a city deep in Virginia's black belt and strong in segregationist sentiment.
Throughout 1962, they repeatedly appeared before the Danville City Council to demand black representation on the boards of city agencies and the end of segregation. In August 1962, Campbell, Dunlap, Adams, and Chase signed the Danville Omnibus Integration Suit, filed in federal court, that called for the integration of Danville's hospitals, schools, cemeteries, public buildings, public housing projects, teaching assignments, and city employment opportunities. On January 1, 1963, Dunlap, Chase, Campbell, Adams, and Pinchback were arrested at a segregated Howard Johnson restaurant for trespassing after refusing to leave when the manager asked them to do so. In March, Martin Luther King, Jr., spoke at a meeting of the Danville SCLC.
On May 31, the Danville civil rights demonstrations began peacefully and ended without incident. Police did not make any arrests and the local press ignored the demonstration. The majority of the demonstrators were teenagers led by Thurman Echols and Ezell Barksdale. On June 5, the demonstrations became more unruly as the participants impeded traffic by sitting down on a main street. Judge Archibald M. Aiken, judge of the Danville Corporation Court, was summoned by police to the scene and commanded the demonstrators to disperse. The demonstrators, however, refused, prompting Aiken to issue a temporary injunction the next day that ordered the demonstrators to desist from, among other things, assembling in an unlawful manner, interfering with traffic and business, obstructing entrances to businesses and public buildings, participating and inciting mob violence, and using loud language that disrupts the peace. The injunction, made permanent a few weeks later, formed the basis for many of the arrests made that summer.
In addition to the injunction, Danville used other methods to quell the demonstrations. A special grand jury, convened by Aiken, indicted the demonstration leaders on June 7 under a slavery-era law called "John Brown's Law" that made inciting "the colored population to acts of violence or war against the white population" illegal. In mid-June and early July, the Danville city council, under the leadership of councilman John W. Carter, an attorney and staunch segregationist, adopted two ordinances designed to limit the demonstrations. One limited the size, place, and time of demonstrations and the other required a permit to parade.
Despite Aiken's and the city council's attempts, the demonstrations continued. Civil rights activists from the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), including field secretaries Bob Zellner, Ivanhoe Donaldson, Avon Rollins, and Daniel Foss of SNCC, and Bruce Baines and Claudia Edwards of CORE arrived in Danville to participate in the demonstrations. Civil rights lawyers affiliated with the National Lawyer's Guild and the NAACP, including William M. Kunstler, Dean Robb, Nathan Conyers, and Samuel W. Tuckers, also arrived in Danville to help represent the demonstrators. On June 10, after a full day of protests, the police, with nightsticks and fire hoses, attacked the demonstrators picketing the city jail. Forty-seven of the fifty demonstrators required medical attention.
The demonstrations continued, however, and by mid-July over 250 people had been arrested on charges of contempt, trespassing, disorderly conduct, assault, parading without a permit, and resisting arrest. Parents were arrested when they went to the jail to post bail for their children for contributing to the delinquency of a minor by not providing adequate supervision.
The defense lawyers, including Len W. Holt, Ruth L. Harvey, Jerry Williams, and Harry I. Wood, in addition to those from the National Lawyer's Guild and the NAACP, attempted to remove the cases from the corporation court to federal court, but to no avail. Each defendant demanded an individual trial causing the corporation court's dockets to be filled to such an extent that cases separate from the demonstrations could not be heard. The prosecutor requested a change of venue to alleviate the crowded docket and Aiken transferred about 124 cases to other courts throughout Virginia.
The defense lawyers again sought an order from the federal courts to stay all arrests, trials, and other proceedings for violation of the injunction and city ordinance. On August 8, the Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals halted these trails pending the outcome of the appeals. Judge Aiken, however, continued hearing the cases for disorderly conduct, parading without a permit, resisting arrest, and trespassing. He generally sentenced the guilty parties to two to five days in jail and a fine, suspending execution of the sentences pending an appeal. In September, defense counsel agreed to consolidate the cases and Aiken rescinded his orders for change of venue.
By mid-August, the demonstrations had largely waned due to Danville's unwillingness to yield to the protests. A year later, the Fourth Circuit Court of Appeal dissolved the injunction, but, by a 3-2 margin and with a strong dissent, declared Aiken's injunction constitutional. Moreover, the cases were remanded to the corporation court where the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals could hear the necessary appeals. The United States Supreme Court upheld the decision by a five-four margin.
In December 1966, Judge Aiken resumed the trials of those who violated his injunction. The trials proceeded quickly. Aiken did not find all the defendants guilty and dismissed some cases for lack of evidence. The usual sentence was eight days in jail and a fine of twenty dollars. The demonstration leaders received the stiffest penalties with Rev. Lawrence G. Campbell receiving the worst, being sentenced 250 days in jail and a $2,500 fine.
In early 1967, the Virginia Supreme Court began deciding the first of the appeals from the Danville Corporation Court. In Thomas v. City of Danville, the Court ruled Judge Aiken's injunction constitutional. In York v. City of Danville, they ruled that a parade can be subject to "reasonable and nondiscriminatory regulation," but that the city's time requirement for applying for a permit was too harsh. In 1970, the Court ruled in Rollins v. Commonwealth that the state must prove that a defendant not named in the injunction had knowledge of the injunction before violating its orders. In January 1973, the Supreme Court of Appeals heard the last of the cases associated with the demonstrations and requested that the Commonwealth's Attorney for Danville review the cases under appeal in light of the court's previous rulings. As a result, the Court overturned the convictions of almost 270 people. However, the Court upheld the convictions of those named in the injunction and for trespassing, obstructing traffic, and illegal picketing.
On February 9, 1973, the court proceedings involving the Danville demonstrations of 1963 came to end. Judge Glynn R. Phillips, Jr. of Clintwood was assigned to hear the defense motion to suspend the jail sentences and fines of those whose convictions had been upheld. Judge Aiken had died in 1971 and the new Danville Corporation Court judge had disqualified himself. Against the prosecutor's objections, Judge Phillips suspended the jail sentences on condition of good behavior for two years, but ordered payment of fines that totaled more than $5,000.
Scope and Content Information
The collection spans the years 1963-1973 and consists of court papers and legal files relating to the 1963 civil rights demonstrations in Danville. These files include bills of particulars, bond records, correspondence, court dockets, court orders, dictabelts, evidence, judgments, petitions, photographs, receipts, subpoenas, and transcripts of testimony that document the legal aspects of the demonstrations from the Danville Corporation Court to the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Individual Case Files, A-Z individual files of persons arrested during the civil rights demonstrations of 1963.
Series II: Howard Johnson Trespassing Case, 1963. concerning the trial for those arrested for trespassing on January 1, 1963 at the Howard Johnson restaurant on Route 29 south of Danville.
Series III:Correspondence, 1963-1967 of clerk of the Danville Corporation Court and clerk of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals
Series IV: Corporation Court Dockets,1963-1967 related to the demonstration cases
Series V: Court Orders, 1963-1973 issued by the Danville Corporation Court and U.S. District Court, Western District of Virginia
Series VI: Evidence, 1963 used in various cases
Series VII: Notes, undated concerning cases and sentencing
Series VIII: Petitions, 1963 Petition for Removal filed with the court
Series IX: Receipts bonds and court costs related to various charges
Series X: Special Grand Jury, 1963 indictments and subpoenas concerning "John Brown's Law"
Series XI: Transcripts, 1963 transcripts of testimony in various cases
Series XII: Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, 1965-1972 decisions handed down by the court of appeals
Series XIII: Dictabelt Records, 1966-1973 audio records of various cases heard in the Danville Corporation Court
Contents List
- Individual Case Files, A-Z (Reel 2325-2327)
  Consists of the individual files of persons arrested during the civil rights demonstrations of 1963. Files include bills of particulars, bond records, judgments, receipts and subpoenas. The files of juveniles arrested include biographical information, including age, education, prior arrests, and family history. The 255 folders are arranged alphabetically by last name.
  Contents arranged alphabetically
  - Folder List:
  - Adams, David
  - Adams, Julius Emanuel
  - Adams, Randy
  - Avery, Annie Pearl
  - Baines, Bruce
  - Banks, Clyde L
  - Barksdale, Ezell
  - Barton, Carolyn Sue
  - Barton, Georgia Jane
  - Beavers, Evelyn Holt
  - Beavers, Hattie M
  - Bethel, Irvin Chris
  - Bethel, Mabel Elizabeth
  - Boone, Percy Bradford
  - Bowe, Clarence Lewis
  - Bradshaw, Lendbury
  - Brown, Harrison, Jr
  - Brown, Luther Alfred
  - Bruce, Everett, Jr
  - Bruce, James Vondell
  - Burrell, Sylvester
  - Cain, Rosa Marie
  - Caldwell, Owen Calvin, Jr
  - Campbell, Lawrence G
  - Canada, Herman
  - Canada, William Burrell, Jr
  - Cardwell, Barbara
  - Carter, Cynthia Ann
  - Carter, Hazel Phyllis
  - Chaney, Claudia Anne
  - Chaney, Connie Lavonne
  - Chappelle, Herman Joseph
  - Chase, Elnora Elizabeth
  - Chase, Lendall Warren
  - Chase, Patricia Glendora
  - Clark, Lelia Virginia
  - Cobb, James, Jr
  - Coleman, Edith Mary
  - Coleman, James Edward
  - Coleman, John Roland
  - Coleman, Lawrence
  - Coleman, Margaret Lee
  - Coleman, Marion Johnson
  - Coleman, Silas
  - Cooke, Veronica Lane
  - Crews, Gilda Patricia
  - Crews, Mary Helen
  - Cunningham, John Thomas
  - Davis, David Lea
  - Davis, Elizabeth
  - Davis, Geneva Rogers
  - Davis, Harvey, Jr
  - Davis, John Lewis
  - Davis, Lizzie Spivey
  - Davis, Mary McAglean
  - Davis, Othia
  - Dawson, Cynthia Anne
  - Denson, Nelly
  - Deshazo, Joyce Ann Lewis
  - Dillard, Margaret P
  - Dixon, Betty Woods
  - Dixon, James, Jr
  - Dodson, Ellis Newton
  - Donaldson, Ivanhoe Gaylord
  - Dunlap, Alexander I
  - Echols, Charlie Henry
  - Echols, Thelma Farmer
  - Edwards, Claudia Jean
  - Elder, Audrey Jean
  - Ferguson, Bobby Lee
  - Ferguson, Ernest David
  - Ferguson, Mildred Luck
  - Ferrell, Lena Emmerson
  - Flemings, Mamie Lee
  - Foss, Daniel Aaron
  - Freeman, Ardelia
  - Gales, Dorothy
  - Gales, George Thomas
  - Gant, Frank Harrison
  - General, Samuel Lawrence
  - Giles, Gladys Virginia
  - Giles, Samuel Wash
  - Glass, Abraham
  - Glass, Archie
  - Glass, Joylette
  - Glass, Lorraine
  - Glass, Thomas Lee Jr
  - Goodwin, Richard Drummond
  - Graves, Carol Delores
  - Graves, Hubert
  - Graves, Mabel
  - Graves, Sylvester
  - Hairston, Annie Mae Lewis
  - Hairston, Charles Jr
  - Hairston, Ennis
  - Hairston, Geraldine
  - Hairston, Jesse
  - Hairston, Joseph Benjamin
  - Hairston, Leatrice Ann
  - Hairston, Penny Jean
  - Hairston, Ralph
  - Hall, Isiah
  - Hamlett, Jimmie
  - Hankins, Laverne
  - Harper, Gladys Marie
  - Harper, Sallie Mae
  - Harris, Gertie Williams
  - Harris, Ola Mae Cunningham
  - Harvest, Joe
  - Hatchett, Joseph Kenneth
  - Heitt, Sallie N
  - Hemphill, Robert, Jr
  - Hodnett, Cheryl Elaine
  - Hoffman, Ronald Leon
  - Holland, Wilma Ann
  - Holloway, Brenda
  - Holloway, Ruby Spraggins Wyllie
  - Holt, Buford Glendale
  - Holt, Grover Cleveland
  - Holt, Leonard Winston
  - Holt, Thomas Cleveland
  - Howard, Violet
  - Hubbard, Lillie Echols
  - Hughes, James Bernard
  - Hughes, Roberta
  - Hughes, Shirley Junior
  - Ingram, William Haywood
  - Jefferies, Iradell Graves
  - Jennings, Maggie Lou
  - Johns, Patrica Ann
  - Johnson, Annie Mae
  - Jones, Hortense
  - Jones, Matthew A
  - Karro, Anne Elliott
  - Kennedy, Penny
  - Kennedy, Sarah Mildred
  - Lancaster, Leslie Wisner
  - Lanier, Willie Terry
  - Lewis, Harry Michael
  - Lewis, Kenneth Lisberg
  - Lewis, Robert James
  - Lewis, Sylvia Ruth
  - Lindsey, Celester
  - Logan, Howard Lee
  - Logan, Orlando
  - Logan, Sally
  - Lumpkin, Dollie J
  - Lumpkin, John Thomas
  - Lumpkin, Otha Frank
  - Lynn, Edna Rose Irby
  - Mabin, Margie
  - Mason, Charlie Henry
  - Mason, Melvin
  - Mason, Myrtle
  - McCain, Daniel
  - McGhee, Evelyn Gray
  - McGhee, George Washington
  - McGhee, Hildreth Glennell
  - McKissick, Lawrence Hance
  - Middlebrook, Harold
  - Mingo, Stuart
  - Moore, Dorothy
  - Moore, Julia Ferguson
  - Moore, Roneatha
  - Morrison, Adell
  - Morton, Marilyn
  - Morton, Robert Lee
  - Murrell, Melba Graves
  - Muse, Maxine Luck
  - Nasper, Louie Martin
  - Page, Delores Jeanette
  - Payne, Charles Henry
  - Peterson, Brian Lee
  - Petty, Archie Lee
  - Pinchback, Arthur Jr
  - Pinchback, John Douglas
  - Pinchback, Larry
  - Pinchback, Margaret Ann
  - Pinchback, Nannie Louise
  - Poteat, Harvey Louis
  - Pounds, Barbara Ann
  - Powell, Rosetta
  - Price, Conrad
  - Price, Mary Laverne
  - Price, Paul
  - Prichett, Luvinia
  - Redd, General
  - Reeves, Marcellous
  - Reid, Milton A
  - Richardson, William Edward
  - Robertson, Delores Ellen
  - Robinson, Odaris
  - Rollins, Avon Williams
  - Saunders, Cordelia Ferguson
  - Saunders, Lonnie McKinley
  - Scales, Blondine Odessa
  - Scales, Don Marie
  - Scales, Dorothy James
  - Scales, James Malcolm
  - Schroeter, Lorraine Coatland Bowe
  - Scott, Earnestine
  - Scott, Geraldine Lee
  - Scott, Sir Walter
  - Scott, William Howard
  - Slade, Azzarie Benson
  - Smith, Dorothy Lee
  - Smith, Ernest Howard
  - Smith, Harvey
  - Smith, Michael
  - Smith, Vernice
  - Still, Elizabeth Phillips
  - Strader, Alice Lee
  - Summers, Maggie
  - Sutherlin, William Thomas
  - Terry, Barbara Ann
  - Terry, Margaret R
  - Terry, Shirley
  - Thomas, Marie
  - Thomas, Willie Ulysses
  - Thompson, Averett Wade
  - Thompson, William
  - Tredinnick, James Harry
  - Via, Dewey Wayne
  - Via, Edgar Lee
  - Via, Virginia Carol
  - Walters, Percy
  - Walters, Ralph Frank
  - Walton, Silvester, Jr
  - Warner, Melvin
  - Watkins, George Albert
  - Wharton, Ronald Eugene
  - Whipple, James Edward
  - White, Mary Etta
  - Wiles, Peggy
  - Williams, Maggie Maxine
  - Williams, Percy Randolph
  - Williams, Undra Ann
  - Wilson, Andrew Lewis
  - Wilson, Ann Gvonne
  - Wilson, Basse, Jr
  - Wilson, Frederick Douglas
  - Wilson, Harry, Jr
  - Wilson, Jacqueline Miller
  - Wilson, Larry James
  - Wilson, Margie Ann
  - Wilson, Melvin
  - Wilson, Rebecca Grasty
  - Womack, Eddie Mae
  - Womack, Estelle
  - Womack, Hester William
  - Womack, William Dexter
  - Wood, Virgil A
  - Woods, Pasadena
  - York, L. Wilson
  - Zellner, John Robert
- Howard Johnson Trespassing Case, 1963 (Reel 2327)
  Includes transcript of testimony and a notice of appeal and assignment of errors relating to the trial of Julius E. Adams, Lawrence G. Campbell, Lendall W. Chase, Alexander I. Dunlap, and Arthur Pinchback, arrested for trespassing on January 1, 1963 at the Howard Johnson restaurant on Route 29 south of Danville.
  Contents arranged chronologically
  - Folder List:
  - Transcript of Testimony, Marrch 1963
  - Notice of Appeal and Assignment of Errors, May 1963
- Correspondence, 1963-1967 (Reel 2327)
  Primarily consists of correspondence between the clerk of the Danville Corporation Court and defense attorney, Ruth L. Harvey, regarding notices of appeal and assignments of errors, and designation of parts of the record. The latter of which she requests the clerk to forward to the clerk of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals. Also, includes correspondence from the clerk of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals indicating receipt of specified materials, and a telegram from the Seattle, Washington branch of the NAACP requesting information on the arrest of Lawrence G. Campbell and Richard D. Goodwin.
  - Folder List:
  - Clerk, Danville Corporation Court, November-December 1963
  - Clerk, Danville Corporation Court, March 1964 - August 1967
  - Clerk, Danville Corporation Court, Seattle NAACP, August 1964
- Corporation Court Dockets (Reel 2327)
  Includes the corporation court's dockets for the demonstration cases from June 1963-April 1967. Lists name of defendant, alleged offense, date of offense, date of trial and disposition of case.
  - Folder List:
  - Criminal Docket, June-September 1963
  - June-July 1963
  - June-August 1963
  - November 1963
  - February 1967
  - April 1967
- Court Orders (Reel 2327-2328)
  Consists of continuances, court orders, judgments, and sentences, issued by the Danville Corporation Court from June 1963-February 1973. Judge Aiken, from June 1963-May 1967, ordered the arrest of demonstrators for violating his injunction and inciting the colored populace, the appearance of demonstrators before the court to answer these violations, the investigation of the juvenile defendants, the serving of jail time and payment of fines, the acquittals of defendants, the consolidation of cases, and the changes of venue. The court orders issued January-February 1973 involved the disqualifying and recusing of the Danville Corporation Judge Stuart L. Craig, the selection of Judge Phillips to replace Craig, the subpoenaing of defense witnesses, and the suspension of jail sentences for the remaining defendants. Also, includes judgements issued by Judge Ted Dalton of the United States District Court for the Western District of Virginia in May 1967.
  - Folder List:
  - June 1963
  - July 1963
  - August 1963
  - September 1963
  - November 1963
  - January - February 1964
  - February - May 1967
  - January - February 1973
  - U.S. District Court, Western District of Virginia, May 1967
- Evidence (Reel 2328)
  Includes the June 7, 1963 issue of the Danville Bee and a note from the paper's general manager indicating the writer and photographer of the June 10, 1963 article entitled. "Thirty Demonstrators Jailed." Also includes excerpts from the July 10, 1963 meeting of the Danville City Council during which it passed an ordinance governing parades, a photocopy of the temporary injunction and restraining order issued by Judge Aiken, and photographs. The photographs show the demonstrators on the steps of city hall, and the arrest of Rev. Lawrence G. Campbell and Thurman Echols.
  Contents arranged alphabetically by material type
  - Folder List:
  - Danville Bee
  - Danville City Council Meeting (excerpts from) - city ordinance governing parades, 1963 July 10
  - Motion, Affidavit, and Order for Temporary Injunction and Restraining Order, 1963 June 6
  - Photographs
- Notes (Reel 2329)
  Includes pieces of papers and lists indicating court cases, dates and places of offenses, trial dates, disposition of cases, and sentences.
  - Folder List:
  - Court Cases, Dates and place of offenses, Trial dates
  - Sentences - Lawrence G. Campbell; Alexander I. Dunlap; Julius E. Adams; Arthur Pinchback, Jr.; Misc.
- Petitions (Reel 2328)
  Consists of the Petition for Removal filed with the clerk of the United States District Court for the Western District of Virginia on June 17, 1963 by defense lawyers Len W. Holt and William M. Kunstler. The petition tried to remove the demonstration cases to federal court.
  - Folder List:
  - Petition for Removal (filed for defendants), 1963 June 17
- Receipts (Reel 2328)
  Includes receipts for bond refunds and payment of fines.
  Contents arranged loosely by the charge
  - Folder List:
  - Bond Refunds
  - Court Costs - Violation State Code Sec. 18.1-14
  - Court Costs - Inducing Minors to commit a Misdemeanor
  - Court Costs - Resisting Arrest
  - Court Costs - Trespassing
  - Court Costs - Violation City Code 16-20 (Parading without a Permit)
  - Court Costs - Violation of City Code Sec. 63 - 7.1, January 1964
  - Court Costs - Miscellaneous
- Special Grand Jury (Reel 2328)
  Includes indictments and subpoenas from the Special Grand Jury responsible for indicting the demonstration leaders under "John Brown's Law." Contains names of the members of the grand jury.
  - Folder List:
  - Affidavit, Indictments, Motion, June 1963
  - Subpoenas, June-August 1963
- Transcripts (Reel 2328-2329)
  Contains transcripts of testimony from:
  Commonwealth of Virginia v. Lawrence G. Campbell,Alexander I. Dunlap, Arthur Pinchback, and Julius Adams, September 19, 1963
  Commonwealth of Virginia v. Lawrence G. Campbell and Alexander I. Dunlap, Violation of Sections 18.1-14 and 18.1-254, October 22, 1963
  Commonwealth of Virginia v. Avon Williams Rollins, August 6, 1963
  City of Danville v. Lawrence G.Campbell, et als, October 1963
  Contents arranged by case
  - Folder List:
  - Commonwealth of Virginia v. Lawrence G. Campbell, A. I. Dunlap, Arthur Pinchback, and Julius Adams, September 1963
  - Commonwealth of Virginia v. Lawrence G. Campbell and A. I. Dunlap, October 1963
  - Commonwealth of Virginia v. Avon Williams Rollins, August 1963
  - City of Danville v. Lawrence G. Campbell, et als (Vol. I, p. 1-399), July- August 1963
  - City of Danville v. Lawrence G. Campbell, et als (Vol. II, p. 400-450), October 1963
  - City of Danville v. Lawrence G. Campbell, et als (Vol. II, p. 451-500), October 1963
  - City of Danville v. Lawrence G. Campbell, et als (Vol. II, p. 501-550), October 1963
  - City of Danville v. Lawrence G. Campbell, et als (Vol. II, p. 551-600), October 1963
  - City of Danville v. Lawrence G. Campbell, et als (Vol. II, p. 601-650), October 1963
  - City of Danville v. Lawrence G. Campbell, et als (Vol. II, p. 651-688), October 1963
- Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals (Reel 2329)